Taft, Philip Papers 5541
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series II. Research/Subject Files
  - Political Candidates, Endorsement of, 1894-1948 (Box 9, Folder 47)
    Several "Memoranda for Mr. Green" from AFL legislative representatives Roberts and Hushing re AFL support of various legislators, 1936-40; letter from AFL President Green to Secretary-Treasurer, Pennsylvania Federation of Labor, exhorting that support for a CIO-backed candidate was treason against the AFL, September 28, 1938; memorandum re Minnesota legislative and congressional campaigns, outlining strategy, budget, 4 pages, October 24, 1947; form letters; notes
  - Political Conventions, Democratic and Republican, 1897-1948 (Box 9, Folder 48)
    "Excerpts from the Declarations of AFL Conventions on Political Action," 1897-1935, 6 pages; numerous AFL recommendations submitted to the platform committees of national Democratic and Republican conventions, 1928-48; form letters; correspondence; notes
  - Price Controls, 1941-1952 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Memorandum to AFL Labor Defense Committee, recommending support of Emergency Price Control Act of 1941; press release, AFL, opposing lifting of price ceilings on restaurant prices, June 17, 1946; statement by AFL Executive Council opposing lifting of price controls generally, June 22, 1946; statements by AFL President Green before Senate Committee on Banking and Currency, March 8, 1945 and April 29, 1946, 4 pages each; statement by AFL legislative representative George D. Riley before House subcommittee on Consumer Price Index, May 21, 1951, 4 pages; form letter; notes
  - Printers, 1950-1956 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    "Printing Industry of America," reprint from American Printer, May, June, July 1951, 11 pages; notes
  - Prohibition (The Volstead Act), 1917-1934 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Letters from AFL President Gompers to President Wilson opposing the Prohibition Act and Volstead Act, December 14, 1917 and October 20, 1919; AFL press release calling for modification of the Volstead Act to allow beer and wine, February 25, 1922, 3 pages; letter to New York Governor Al Smith from AFL President Gompers, urging repeal of state law enforcing Volstead Act, May 29, 1923; letter from AFL President Green to President urging manufacture and sale of beer, December 22, 1925; statements by AFL legislative representative W. C. Roberts before legislative committees, describing Volstead Act as cause of crime, blindness and insanity, likening it to Soviet program of institutionalizing atheism by thought-control of the young, urging sale of beer and wine, 1926, 8 pages and c. 1929, 9 pages; correspondence
  - Public Works, 1888-1938 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Memoranda to AFL President Green from AFL legislative committee or legislative representative re public works projects, 1926 and 1938; minutes of AFL Executive Council re proposed legislation requiring payment of prevailing wages on government construction projects, with letter from President, Bricklayers, Masons and Plasterers' International Union and copy of bill attached, January 9, 1930, 5 pages; form letter from AFL Building Trades Department re agreement by federal government to pay prevailing wages on construction, August 25, 1933; notes
  - Puerto Rico, 1901-1949 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    "Legislation Demanded by the Workers of Puerto Rico," 3 page unsigned report, probably by AFL legislative committee or representative, n.d., c. 1910; Resolution by Puerto Rican Free Federation of Workingmen delegate re minimum wages in Puerto Rico, especially in textile industry, recommending extension of mainland U.S. wage-hour law to Puerto Rico, 1949; notes
  - Quarry Workers, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Racketeering, 1898-1959 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Correspondence between AFL President Green and various officials of the Iron Workers' Local, Newark, New Jersey, and with President, International Association of Bridge and Structural Iron Workers, re charges of racketeering, July-August 1932, 20 pages; memorandum from AFL legislative representative re anti-racketeering bill, November 12, 1934, 5 pages; letter to AFL President Green re anti-racketeer bill and suggested amendments, May 15, 1934; letter to AFL President Green from United Mine Workers official re anti-racketeering bill as threat to bona fide labor, April 21, 1934; "Report on Certain Aspects of Labor Union Responsibility and Control," prepared by a subcommittee of the Committee on Legislation of the City Club of New York City, June 8, 1937, 23 pages; "Analysis of ... Hobbs Bill" amending Anti-Racketeering Act of 1934, by AFL General Council, recommending opposition, May 20, 1942, 4 pages; "Report on Trade Union Courier," 10 page report by AFL Executive Council re unethical practices of Trade Union Courier, c. 1948; letter from Editor of Trade Union Courier to AFL Vice-President Matthew Woll, praising and defending the paper, June 22, 1948, 8 pages; "In the Matter of ..." finding of New York State Labor Relations Board against sham labor union, outlines criteria for determining legitimacy of labor unions under law, July 16, 1959; "AFL-CIO Codes of Ethical Practices," printed booklet, February 1957; "Building Service Employees' International Union In the Bronx: A History of Corruption," 29 page report covering period from 1912-64 re Mafia control of local 32E; letter to AFL President Green, printed in Chicago Daily News, 1940 re corruption in local, with attached letter from CIO President John L. Lewis' secretary; three page manuscript, numbered 3-5, probably by Taft re extortion case Postman vs. International Brotherhood of Teamsters, 1964; several from letters re AFL position on racketeering; notes. See also: Bakery and Confectionery Workers - Corruption, Box 3, File Folder 45. See also: Teamsters - Publications, Box 13, File Folder 3-5
  - Racketeering - Clippings, 1941-1954 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Racketeering - International Longshoremen's Association, 1952-1953 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Report to President Green by AFL committee appointed to evaluate report of New York State Board of Inquiry re labor troubles in the Port of New York, August 7, 1952, 9 pages; letter to President Meany from AFL Vice-President David Dubinsky calling for more action on part of Executive Council in dealing with troubles in International unions, December 20, 1952, and reply, January 15, 1953; four long, detailed press statements by ILA Executive Council, January 7, 8, 9, and 11, 1953; minutes of AFL Executive Council, with communication delivered to ILA, February 3, 1953, 3 pages, reply, May 15, 1953, 13 pages, reply to reply, stating that it was inadequate, May 26, 1953, 5 pages; "Excerpts from the Record of the Public Hearings Held by Governor Thomas E. Dewey on the Recommendations of the New York State Crime Commission For Remedying Condition on the Waterfront of the Port of New York," June 8 and 9, 1953; testimony of AFL President Meany, 12 pages; letter from AFL President Meany to ILA Executive Council notifying of intent to suspend affiliation until ILA implements reforms, August 11, 1953; notes. See also: Maritime - Longshoremen - New York City/New York State Reports, Box 8, File Folder 17-17a
  - Radio Workers, 1933-1936 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Railroads - Legislation, 1917-1950 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    "Labor Relations in the Railroad Industry in the United States," unsigned manuscript, 3/27/53, 12 pages; minutes of meeting with AFL legislative committee and Congressman re repeal of Esch-Cummings Law, February 27, 1924, 6 pages; "Extract from Minutes of Executive Council Meeting ... January 8-17, 1930"; "Preliminary Analysis and Statement Respecting S 3463 - the Donnell Bill Prohibiting Strikes and Providing For Compulsory Arbitration in the Railroad Industry," AFL statement, n.d., 4 pages; statement of AFL President Green before Senate Committee on Education and Labor, against Donnell Bill, June 10, 1950, 3 pages; notes
  - Railroads - Unions - General (Box 10, Folder 12)
    "The Brotherhood of Railway Trainmen," unsigned typescript ("paid 10-7-53"), 5 pages; two page description by black employee of the Panama Canal / Panama Railroad Co. re efforts of "two white organizers" from the United Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way and Railway Shop Laborers to organize black workers; includes description of resistance by white labor unions, response of AFL, and successful result, unsigned, May 22, 1919; much correspondence between AFL President Gompers and officials of various rail unions, 1918-21; "Remarks of Samuel Gompers Before Conference of the Executives of the Railroad Organizations Affiliated with the AFL and the Four Brotherhoods," February 10, 1920, 17 pages; notes
  - Railroads - Unions, Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, 1924-1952 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    "The Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees," unsigned typescript ("paid, 4-5-52"), 9 pages; correspondence re reaffiliation/jurisdictional dispute between Teamsters and Railway and Steamship Clerks, May 1928; Notes
  - Railway Pamphlets, 1887-1946 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Receivership - Notes, 1932-1940 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Reciprocal Trade, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Reconversion, 1944-1946 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    Memos from AFL legislative representative re various bills July 1944; summary of bill for national reconversion, August 24, 1944, 6 pages; "Joint Letter from AFL, CIO and Railway Labor Executives Association," supporting Kilgore Bill, sent to all Senators, May 1, 1944, 2 pages; statements by AFL Vice-President Matthew Woll: ("Machinery For Reconversion," before Subcommittee of the U.S. Senate Military Affairs Committee, April 4, 1944, 16 pages; "Remobilizing For Peace," before U.S. Senate Post-War Economic Policy and Planning Committee, May 15, 1944, 21 pages); statement by AFL President Green in support of bill re disposal of government surplus with proposed amendments, August 9, 1944, 5 pages; "Statement re George Bill ... as Referred to House Committee on Ways and Means," August 17, 1944, by unnamed AFL representative; AFL Weekly News Service, excerpted articles, February 1945, and whole issue, April 3, 1945; minutes of AFL Executive Council with letter from FDR commanding formation of committee of industry and labor, March 28, 1945; "Statement by Lewis G. Hines, National Legislative Representative, AFL, Presented to the Committee on Post-War Military Policy," June 13, 1945, against compulsory military training, 8 pages; excerpts of address by AFL President Green at annual dinner of Carbondale Central Labor Union, against government regulation of the economy, March 14, 1946, 3 pages; statement by AFL President Green before the Special Subcommittee of the House Labor Committee, July 1, 1946 re strikes July 1, 1946, 9 pages; notes
  - Religion, 1902-1921 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    Letter from the American Federation of Catholic Societies, calling for closer, formal relations with AFL, January 12, 1915, 3 pages; notes
  - Rent Control, 1949-1950 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    Letter "to all Central Labor Unions" with "Major Provisions in the 1949 Rent Control Law" attached, April 14, 1949; press release, statement by AFL President Green opposing increase in "fair net operating income" standard for landlords, May 4, 1949; "Statement by William Green, President, AFL, Before the Senate Committee on Banking and Currency on the Extension of Rent Control," April 26, 1950.
  - Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Employees, 1942-1968 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Right-to-Work Laws, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Rubber Workers, 1935-1942 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Sacco-Vanzetti Case, 1926-1927 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Scottsboro Case, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Seniority - Notes, 1916-1955 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Shipbuilding Stabilization Board, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Social Insurance - Old Age Pensions, Health, Unemployment Insurance, etc.), 1907-1955 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    Three "memos for Mr. Green" from AFL legislative representatives re status of old age pension legislation in various states, January 29, 1933, status of workmen's compensation legislation in various states, January 29, 1934, and analysis of unemployment insurance bill, December 6, 1935; statement by AFL President Green before the Senate Committee on Finance, in support of supplementary unemployment compensation, August 29, 1945, 14 pages; statement by AFL representative before House Ways and Means Committee in support of expanded unemployment compensation, June 5, 1946, 7 pages; summary of National Health Insurance and Public Health Act, May 31, 1949, 6 pages; "The Need for a Federal Unemployment Compensation Standards Bill," with summary of Act, 13 pages, [1954]; many form letter and notes
  - Social Security, 1935-1957 (Box 10, Folder 28)
    Letter from AFL President Green to Senator LaFollette, opposing amendment to Social Security bill exempting contribution by employers offering private retirement plans; letter from AFL President Green to U.S. Civil Service Commission, urging that labor representatives be allowed to serve on Social Security Board, January 16, 1937, reply clarifying regulations, January 29, 1937, 4 pages; report of the AFL Committee on Social Security, January 26, 1939, 3 pages; testimony by AFL Vice-President Matthew Woll before the House Ways and Means Committee re revisions in social security, March 7, 1939, 8 pages, and by AFL legislative representative, March 9, 1939, 3 pages (both sent as package with cover letter from AFL President Green to all State Federations and Central Labor Unions); letter from AFL President Green to Chairman House Ways and Means Committee re need for federally-administrated unemployment compensation, January 26, 1942; letter from AFL legislative representative to Congressman re federalization of unemployment compensation, February 6, 1942; letter to AFL President Green from AFL legislative representative re payroll deduction increase for social security, November 27, 1944; letter from AFL President Green to member of Senate finance Committee opposing freeze on payroll deductions for social security, December 6, 1944; statement adopted by the AFL Executive Council protesting reorganization plan of Federal Security Agency, May 22, 1946; statement by AFL to House Ways and Means Committee re public assistance aspects of social security, March 18, 1949, 7 pages; statement by AFL representative before House Ways and Means Committee in support of revisions in social security system, April 20, 1949, 7 pages; report of AFL Committee on Social Security, February 7, 1950; statement by AFL representative before Senate Finance Committee in support of revisions in social security system, March 1, 1950, 6 pages; letter from AFL Vice-President Matthew Woll to Senator Herbert H. Lehman clarifying position of AFL re coverage of state and local government employees under social security, March 20, 1950; statement of AFL position re revisions in social security, May 26, 1950, 5 pages; report of Committee on Social Security to AFL Executive Council, February 1953; "The Conception, Gestation and Birth of the Social Security Department [AFL]," July 12, 1957, 7 pages, (frank discussion by AFL Director, Department of Social Security, prepared for P. Taft, re personalities involved in AFL activities).
  - Socialists, 1881-1920 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Sound Money, 1896-1933 (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Southern Labor, 1928-1948 (Box 10, Folder 31)
    Letter to AFL President Green from AFL organizer George L. Googe, describing extensive activities in organizing textile mills in Georgia, May 27, 1929, 7 pages; report of AFL Southern Organizing Campaign Committee meeting of November 16, 1930; report on the Southern Campaign by Chairman George L. Googe, May 11-12, 1946, 7 pages; "Memorandum for the Press - Re: CIO Organizing Campaign in the South," May 3, 1946, 3 pages; "Report of CIO Southern Campaign Staff," prepared by AFL Southern representative George L. Googe, n.d.; "Report to the AFL Executive Council on the Southern Campaign - George L. Googe, Chairman," July 31, 1947, 13 pages; "Confidential to Members of the Executive Council: Expenditures Since Report to April 1947 Meeting of the Executive Council" and "Financial Report of Total Campaign Expenditures of Southern Organizing Campaign May 1, 1946 to August 1, 1947," by George L. Googe; "Who Are These Dixiecrats?" 7 page manuscript adopted by the annual convention of the Alabama State CIO Political Action Committee, October 17, 1948; notes
  - Spinners Union, 1879-1902 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Stationery Firemen, 1898 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Steam Shovel and Dredgemen, International, 1914 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Steel - Communists, Negroes, Handbills, Miscellaneous, 1918-1943 (Box 10, Folder 35)
    Handbills: ("Colored Steel Workers", "CIO Steel Workers Mass Meeting", "Steel Workers - Are You Satisfied?" by Steel Workers Organizing Committee, "What's the Score? On Negotiations" by United Steelworkers); "General Report on Steel Strike Relief Fund," by William Z. Foster, Secretary-Treasurer, National Committee for Organizing Iron and Steel Workers, January 31, 1920 and report on newly organized steel workers by location and trade from August 1, 1918 to January 31, 1920, by William Z. Foster; letter from John P. Davis, National Secretary, National Negro Congress, to William Mitch, United Mine Workers re organizing black steel workers, October 12, 1936; numerous memoranda by V.R. Tompkins (most unsigned), some addressed to AFL Metal Trades Department Director John Frey, re Communist party activity within Steel Workers Organizing Committee, 1936-1937; miscellaneous memoranda re SWOC activities, 1936; miscellaneous papers
  - Steel - Iron, Steel and Tin Workers, Amalgamated Association, 1910-1936 (Box 10, Folder 36)
    "Status of Iron, Steel and Tin Workers' Struggle with the U.S. Steel Corporation," c. 1910, 9 pages; letter from AFL President Samuel Gompers to President Taft re charges against U.S. Steel, January 6, 1910, and reply from the U.S. Attorney General March 28, 1910; resolution sent to AFL President Gompers and U.S. Secretary of Labor by convention of Amalgamated Association of Iron, Steel and Tin Workers asking for investigation of conditions at striking California plant, c. 1917; "Memorandum for Mr. Green" from AFL legislative representative W. C. Roberts re open shop provision for steel industry in the National Industrial Recovery Bill, July 28, 1933; letter to William Green re radical elements at 60th convention of the Amalgamated Association of Iron, Steel and Tin Workers, April 24, 1935; list of AAISTW locals suspended for non-payment of per capita tax, May 4, 1935; correspondence between AFL President Green, AAISTW President Tighe and members of expelled locals re reinstatement, August 1935; correspondence re agreement reached at conference for reinstatement and payment of back taxes, September-October 1935; minutes of the AFL Executive Council re Amalgamated per capita tax, organizing problems, October 1935; "Suggested Plan to Organize the Steel Industry submitted to Executive Council of the American Federation of Labor by the International Executive Board, AAISTW of North America," October 20, 1935, 11 pages; "Summary of Situation in Steel, January 13, 1936," unsigned, 8 pages; letter to AFL President Green from John L. Lewis proposing plan for organizing steel workers, offering financial assistance, February 22, 1936, and reply, that letter was being referred to Executive Council, February 25, 1936; "Replies to letter of March 2, 1936, to Presidents of National and International Unions," soliciting contributions to AFL steel organizing drive: union-by-union breakdown of replies, with comments, 6 pages; letter to Af President of AAISTW from John L. Lewis, repeating offer of assistance, April 15, 1936; "Iron, Steel and Tin Workers Organizing Campaign," excerpts from minutes of AFL Executive Council, rejecting "Suggested Plan" (above) submitted by AAISTW for organizing steel industry, May 5, 1936; letter to AAISTW convention from AFL President Green that AFL Executive Council would organize steelworkers without "interference" from any other organization, May 8, 1936; telegram to AAISTW convention from John L. Lewis, in reply to letter from President Green, criticizing AFL position as futile and malicious, reiterating offer of support, May 8, 1936; telegram to AAISTW convention from AFL President Green, replying to Lewis' reply to Green's first letter, denying malice, May 11, 1936; letter to AAISTW from John L. Lewis, urging speed in carrying out decision of convention in favor of CIO, May 21, 1936; statement by AAISTW Executive Board announcing upcoming meeting with John L. Lewis, unsatisfactory response from other unions, June 4, 1936; statement by AFL President Green (as press release), decrying decision by AAISTW to accept CIO plan, June 5, 1936, and similar statement, denouncing CIO's "thwarting" of AFL's organizing effort, July 8, 1936; correspondence between AAISTW President Tighe and President, International Association of Bridge and Structural Workers (AFL), that CIO was doing virtually all organizing of steel workers, July 30-31, 1936; letter from AAISTW President Tighe to AFL President Green re revocation of AAISTW charter by AFL, May 30, 1938, 3 pages.
  - Steel - Steel Workers' Organizing Committee (SWOC), 1936-1943 (Box 10, Folder 37)
    List of SWOC personnel, July 19, 1939, 12 pages; "Tennessee Coal, Iron and Railroad Co. Agreement," March 17, 1937, 7 pages; letter to AFL President Green from United Mine Workers President Van Bittner, excoriating Green's "treachery to labor" in opposing CIO organization of steel industry, July 22, 1937; "Officers' Report to the First Constitutional Convention," 12 page report of history and activities of SWOC's Southern District, May 9, 1942, with 3 page list of Meetings of Steel Lodges; list of new lodges and SWOC membership, 10 pages, January 1, 1937; correspondence by SWOC Executive Director Noel Beddow, thanking for financial support of strikers, inviting employee representatives of company unions to SWOC meeting, 1936-38; "Minutes of Meeting Held in the Office of Acting Manager of Industrial Relations," re terms of 1941 agreement between SWOC and Tennessee Coal, Iron and Railroad Co., May 13, 1941, 3 pages; "Memorandum of Meeting Held in Office of Acting Manager of Industrial Relations, April 7, 1942" with agreement between SWOC and Tennessee Coal, Iron and Railroad Co., 3 pages; "Minutes of Meeting with Grievance Committee of the SWOC" re request for pay increase at Tennessee Coal, Iron, and Railroad Co., April 10, 1942; "Plan of Employee Representation in Plants of Tennessee Coal, Iron and Railroad Co.," n.d., 8 pages; letter from SWOC Executive Director re stripper incident at Gadsden, Alabama steel mill, with clipping of newspaper account, March 2, 1940; letter from SWOC Executive Director to Lee Pressman, General Counsel, CIO, re situation at Republic Steel plant, May 13, 1941; "Secretaries of Steel Lodges in Birmingham," 1936; "Statement by Philip Murray, November 8, 1936: The Problem Before the SWOC on June 17, 1936," 7 pages; "Minutes of a Meeting of the SWOC Held in Pittsburgh, PA, September 29, 1936," 4 pages, with "Philip Murray, Chairman, report to the SWOC," 6 pages, and summary, 3 pages; letter to SWOC Chairman Philip Murray from Regional Director William Mitch re situation at Gadsden, Alabama plant with legal opinion attached, May 18, 1937; "Report of Southern Region of the SWOC Organizing Committee for the CIO Conference, October 11, 1937, 7 pages; "First Wage and Policy Convention of the SWOC," December 14-16, 1937, 5 pages; "Proceedings of the Second International Wage and Policy Convention of the SWOC, May 14-17, 1940, 8 pages; letter to CIO President Philip Murray from Regional Director Noel Beddow re racial trouble at Southern steel plant, July 12, 1943; telegram to Beddow from Secretary-Treasurer urging caution by lodge officers in dealing with U.S. Steel plant managers, August 8, 1939; SWOC pamphlet, "The U.S. Supreme Court's Decision in the Republic Steel Case," directed at employees, 1937; form letters. See also: Steel - Communists, etc., Box 10, File Folder 35.